(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-08-01T20:33:38.701033",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
真っ赤な夕空
The crimson evening sky
青くなる星
The stars turning blue
心臓を焦がして 冷めない温度
Burning my heart, the temperature that won't cool down
半端に零した 声の残響と
The reverberations of a voice incompletely spilled
半端に混ざった 花の色
And the color of flowers mixed in halfway
きっと立ち止まって 芽を伸ばしたって
Even if I stop and let buds grow
咲いた瞬間 散ってしまうのでしょう
They will probably scatter the moment they bloom
いっそどれも 素敵な景色なんだって
I wish I could have thought that
きっとそんな風に 思えたらよかったって
Even that is a lovely scene
言えない
I can't say it
「さよなら」なんて
I can't say "goodbye" yet
まだ言えないまま 魔法が解けていく
As the magic wears off
バラバラになって 花になって
Falling apart, becoming flowers
風に溶けていく
Melting into the wind
手を振れないまま 黙って立っている
I'm standing here silently, unable to wave my hand
私を忘れて すぐに
Forget about me immediately
伝えたい想いを 声に出したって
Even if I try to voice the feelings I want to convey
こんな言葉 なんて言えないんだろう
Why can't I say words like these?
大事にしてしまうから ずっと
Because I treasure you so much, forever
大事なことが 伝わらないんじゃないかって
I'm afraid the important things won't get across
知らない
I don't know
知りたくもないことばかりで
Things I don't even want to know
胸が裂けていく
Are tearing my chest apart
ズタズタになって 怖いぐらいに
Falling to pieces, becoming so fearful
愛しくなっていく
It becomes so dear
手も触れないまま 不確かにしてしまう
I make it uncertain, without even touching
ごめんね ごめんね
I'm sorry, I'm sorry
いつか時間が経ってみたら
If some time passes someday
何でもないって 顔をして
I'll put on a face like it's nothing
寂しさも痛みすらも
Even the loneliness, even the pain
抜け落ちて 過去になる
Will fall out and become the past
いつしかそんな日が来たら
If such a day comes someday
そんな時間が来るのなら
If such a time comes
だったら今は
Then, right now
どうしようもないぐらい 君を想っている
I am thinking of you, uncontrollably
思い出になんてならないぐらい
To the extent that you won't become a memory
君で出来ている
You are made of you
ずっと気づいていた 気づいてしまったんだ
I'd noticed it all along, I'd realized it
「忘れて」なんてね 嘘だ
"Forget about me"—that's a lie
愛しさが胸を焦がしていく
The love burns my heart
傷になったって 覚えていて
Even if it becomes a wound, remember me
忘れないでいて
Please don't forget me
もう言えないから 今、喉を伝う
Since I can't say it anymore, now, it travels down my throat
笑ってまた会おうね
Let's laugh and meet again
さよなら
Goodbye
なんでもないや
Caught in a never-ending game,
僕らはいかに気まぐれに世界を救ってきたことか
Seems like the world's still trying to tame me
何十回何百回と君の姿を思い描いては
If that's the way, I will obey...
十字路を見上げていたんだよ
Beautifully struggle every day
街の景色はまるで一幕の芝居のようで
Shouldn't we have a little kiss?
いつの間にか僕らはその主役になっていた
While seeing both of our hourglasses.
ついにその時が来たんだ
Finally the time has come—
昨日までのすべてがプロローグだったように
Everything up to yesterday was a prologue
ありふれた日々に別れを告げよう
Just skimmin' through the days of old,
新しい物語の始まりだ
It's my turn to bear the load
忘れていた勇気を胸に抱いて
My experience and my skill... and all the courage I had left started to mildew
僕は今君のもとへと走り出すんだ
At an unprecedented speed, I will dive right into you
誰もが羨むようなストーリーじゃなくていい
And when I go and stomp into a lukewarm can of soda
僕らだけの足跡を刻んでいこう
I dreamed of a world so far from here that's not on the map
どんな困難が待ち受けていようとも
Searching outside of the classroom window...
二人なら乗り越えられるさ
Or in a summer morning that's brought open by a commuting train
未来は僕らの手の中にあるんだから
Words like "tomorrow" or "future" or "fate"...
さあ行こう、新しい世界へ
No matter how far they extend their hands
振り返ればたくさんの思い出が蘇る
Let's put 'em away, then bow our heads—
泣いたことも笑ったことも全部宝物だ
“How do you do”s and all the “nice to meet you”s
一緒に過ごした日々は永遠の輝きを放つ
And breathe over a thousand years, cycled in a single day.
だからこそ、今日のこの瞬間を大切にしたい
Oh, how I hated life in this world.
みんな本当にありがとう
It's made up entirely of fiction, every word stacked
これからの未来が素晴らしいものでありますように
I saw through my kaleidoscope on a monotonous august morn'
さようなら、そしてありがとう
When you appeared in front of me, you acted shy,
未来は僕らの手の中にあるんだから
Words like "tomorrow" or "future" or "fate"...
さあ行こう、新しい世界へ
No matter how far they extend their hands
いつまでも、いつまでも
We breathe, we dream, we raise our love...
僕らの心は一つだから
In a timeless land that is far out of reach
忘れないよ、この絆を
Even the second, hour hands of the clock;
輝ける未来へ、羽ばたいていこう
They look at us sideways as they tick and tock.
最高の時間をありがとう
How I hope to have forever to spend this life—no, all future lives!
大好きだよ
Right here in this world, with you.
今宵も頭上では
Even tonight, overhead,
綺麗な満月がキラキラ
a beautiful full moon sparkles brilliantly,
幸せそうに世界を照らしている
shining upon the world as if to bring happiness.
今の私は 出来損ないでどうしようもなくて
As I am now, good-for-nothing and helpless,
夜明け夢見ては 地べた這いずり回っている
I dream of daybreak, crawling along the ground.
それでも誰かに見つけてほしくて
Even so, wanting someone to find me,
夜空見上げて叫んでいる
I look up at the night sky and cry out.
逃げ出したいな 逃げ出せない
I want to run away, but I can't escape.
明るい未来は見えないね
I can't see a bright future.
それでもあなたに見つけて欲しくて
Even so, wanting you to find me,
蝶のように舞い上がるの
I soar up into the sky like a butterfly,
欠けた翼で飛んだ
flying with clipped wings—
醜い星の子ミカヅキ
an ugly star's crescent moon.
今宵も頭上では
Tonight overhead,
綺麗な満月がゆらゆら
the beautiful full moon sways.
誰かの腕に抱かれて 眠っている
Sleeping in someone's arms,
当の私は ひとりの夜に押し潰されては
While I am crushed by the lonely night,
誰にも見えない 夜闇這いずり回っている
crawling through the unseen darkness.
それでも誰にも負けたくなくて 宇宙の隅で藻掻いている
Still, not wanting to lose to anyone, I struggle in the corner of the cosmos.
追いつきたいや 追い越したい 夢を見たような世界ね
Wanting to catch up, wanting to overtake—what a dreamy world.
それでも誰かと比べてばっか 周りを見ては立ち止まって
Still, just comparing myself to others, stopping every time I look around.
欠けたものを探した そんな自分を変えたい
I searched for what was missing; I want to change myself like that.
それでもあなたと同じ景色が また見たいから
Still, because I want to see the same scenery with you again—
泣き出したくても 投げ出したくても 諦めたりはできない
Even if I want to cry, even if I want to give up, I can't just surrender.
それでもあなたに見つかるように サナギは強く手を伸ばすの
Still, so that you can find me, the chrysalis reaches out its hand strongly.
欠けたもの抱きしめて 願いを放つよミカヅキ
Embracing what's missing, releasing my wish, Mikazuki.
それでも誰かに見つけてほしくて 夜空見上げて叫んでいる
Still, wanting someone to find me, I look up at the night sky and cry out.
泣き出したいけど 泣き出さない もう後戻りなどできないね
Wanting to start crying, but holding back tears—there's no turning back now.
それでもあなたに見つけてほしくて 蝶のように舞い上がるの
Still, wanting you to find me, I soar upward like a butterfly.
欠けた翼で飛ぶよ 醜い星の子ミカヅキ 光を放ったミカヅキ
Flying with chipped wings, Mikazuki, child of an ugly star, Mikazuki that emitted light.
今宵も頭上では 綺麗な満月がキラキラ
Tonight overhead, the beautiful full moon sparkles.
次は君の番だと 笑っている
Smiling, saying it's your turn next.
「こんな世界」と嘆く誰かの 生きる理由になれるでしょうか
In a world where someone laments "such a world", could I become their reason to live?
これは僕がいま君に贈る 最初で最後の愛の言葉だ
This is the first and last word of love I send to you now.
街も人も歪み出した 化け物だったと気付いたんだ
The town and people distorted, I realized they were monsters.
欲動に巣食った愚かさも すべてがこの目に映る
Even the foolishness bred in desire, everything reflects in these eyes.
シアトリカルに手の上で 誰彼も踊らされる
Theatrically on the palm of a hand, everyone is made to dance.
生まれた意味だって知らぬまま 形骸化した夢は錆びついてしまった
Without even knowing why I was born, my ossified dream has rusted away.
「愛をください」 きっと誰かがそう願った
"Give me love"—surely someone wished for that.
「愛をください」 そっと震えた手を取って
"Give me love"—taking a softly trembling hand.
「愛をください」 心を揺るがす 醜いくらいに美しい愛を
"Give me love"—a love that shakes the heart, as beautiful as it is ugly.
「こんな世界」と嘆く誰かの 生きる理由になれるでしょうか
In a world where someone laments "such a world", could I become their reason to live?
いつか終わると気付いた日から 死へと秒を読む心臓だ
From the day I realized everything ends, this heart counts down the seconds to death.
「こんな世界」と嘆く誰かの
For someone lamenting, "Such a world,"
生きる理由になれるでしょうか
could I become the reason they live?
これは僕がいま君に贈る
This is what I'm giving you now,
最初で最後の愛の言葉だ
my first and last words of love.
街も人も歪み出した
The town and people began to warp,
けもの道に巣食った愚かさも
and the foolishness nestled in the beast paths—
全てがこの目に映る
everything reflects in these eyes,
シアトリカルに手の上で
theatrically in the palm of my hand,
誰も彼も踊らされる
making anyone and everyone dance.
生まれた意味だって知らぬまま
Without even knowing the meaning of being born,
形骸化した夢は錆びついてしまった
dreams that became mere skeletons have rusted away.
「愛をください」
"Please give me love,"
きっと誰もがそう願った
surely everyone wished for that.
「愛をください」
"Please give me love."
「こんな世界」と嘆く誰かの
For someone lamenting, "Such a world,"
生きる理由になれるでしょうか
could I become the reason they live?
いつか終わると気付いた日から 死へと秒を読む心臓だ
A heartbeat counting down to death since the day I realized it would end someday.
ねえ このまま雨に溺れて 藍に溶けたって構わないから
Hey, if I drown in the rain like this and dissolve into indigo, I wouldn't mind.
どうか どうか またあの日のように 傘を差し出し笑ってみせてよ
Please, please, just like that day, hold out an umbrella and smile for me.
もしもし夢が覚めなければ
If only this dream wouldn't awaken,
姿を変えずにいられた？
could I have stayed without changing my form?
ほどけた指から消える温度
The warmth fading from intertwined fingers—
血を巡らせるのは誰の思い出？
whose memories are making the blood circulate?
雨に濡れた廃線
Rain-soaked abandoned tracks,
煤けた病棟 並んだ送電塔
soot-stained wards, and lined power transmission towers.
夕暮れのバス 止まったままの観覧車
A dusk bus, a Ferris wheel stuck in place—
机に咲く花 君の声も
the flowers blooming on the desk, and your voice,
何もかも最初から無かったみたい
as if none of it ever existed from the start.
死たい僕は今日も息をして
Wanting to die, I breathe again today;
生きたい君は明日を見失って
wanting to live, you lost sight of tomorrow.
なのに どうして悲しいのだろう
Yet, why is it so sad?
いずれ死ぬのが人間だ
Humans are bound to die eventually.
永遠なんてないけれど
Though there is no such thing as eternity,
思い通りの日々じゃないけれど
and days don't go quite as expected,
脆く弱い糸に繋がれた 次の夜明けがまた訪れる
connected by fragile threads, the next dawn visits once more.
はい、というわけで
Yes, and with that,
え？
Eh?
なんだこれ？
What is this?
このライブ2期生 紫咲シオンさん 至急校長室まで来てください。
This is a message for 2nd gen's Murasaki Shion. Please report to the principal's office immediately.
えー、めんどくさい！なんで？
Jeez, what a pain! Why?
仕方ないですね。
Can't be helped.
何に？すごい！
To what? Amazing!
なんだこれ、めっちゃきれい！
What is this? It's so pretty!
シオンさん、こちらへどうぞ。
Shion-san, right this way.
やぐさんだ！
It's Yagoo!
はい。
Yes.
卒業証書 紫咲シオン 12月8日生まれ
Certificate of Graduation: Murasaki Shion, born December 8th.
あなたは魔界学校の課程を修了しましたのでここに証します。 令和7年4月26日 谷郷元昭
You have completed the Demon World School curriculum, hereby certified. April 26, Reiwa 7. Principal Motoaki Tanigo.
うん。
Mm.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
みんな見てー！もらっちゃった！卒業証書！
Everyone look! I got it! A graduation certificate!
すごい！
Amazing!
うそ、これ
No way, this...
なになに？
What, what?
え、まだわたしてものがあるの？
Eh, you still have something to give me?
シオンさん、お疲れ様です。また配信をよよのファンの皆様、いつも応援ありがとうございます。
Shion-san, thank you for your hard work. And to all the fans watching the stream, thank you always for your support.
カバー株式会社の谷郷元昭です。
I am Motoaki Tanigo, CEO of Cover Corp.
本物が？
The real deal?
そういえば、質問を預かってきています。 免許はMTですか？ATですか？
Which reminds me, I have some questions entrusted to me. Is your driver's license manual or automatic?
免許はマニュアルですね。
My license is manual.
おー、よかった！
Oh, great!
え、なんかあるのかな？
Eh, is there something?
他バーの免許は持ってないです。
I don't hold any other-bar licenses.
あー、車なんだね。
Ah, cars.
え、これ気になる！どうしよう。
Eh, I'm curious about this! What should I do?
配信者として魅力を感じたからですね。ま、ちょっとおちゃめな感じのところがいいですね。
Because I felt your charm as a streamer. Well, the somewhat playful side of you is nice.
なぜ私に声をかけたのか気になります！理由はありますか？
Why did you reach out to me? I'm curious! Is there a reason?
あ、そうなんだ、そうなんだね。逆にね。
Oh, is that so? In a way, yeah.
あ、これ気になるよね。
Ah, I'm curious about this too.
やはりあの、ボカロPとか歌い手さんがしっかり定着していったように、ま、VTuberも、あの、これからの10年とかかけてしっかり職業として定着すればいいなと思ってます。
Just as Vocaloid producers and utaites have firmly established themselves, I hope VTubers will also firmly establish themselves as a profession over the next decade.
さすが社長っぽいこと、っぽいこと？ぽいというか、社長、社長だな。
That sounds so CEO-like... Well, you really are the CEO.
そうですね、ま、日本だったり、あの、世界のあの、人たちにとって、ま、ホロライブっていうものがそのVTuberを、ま、代表するような、あの、存在に、ま、なっていて、ま、皆様に憧れていただけるような、ま、そういいう存在になっていればいいなと思っております。
That's right. I hope Hololive becomes a presence that represents VTubers for people in Japan and around the world, and becomes someone everyone can look up to.
あ、世界制服かと思ったわ。世界って言ったから。
Ah, I thought you said world domination, since you said "the world."
シオンさん、改めてまして、今まで長い間活動お疲れ様でした。最後の配信、頑張ってくださいね。
Shion-san, once again, thank you for all your hard work over such a long time. Please do your best on your final stream.
ありがとうございます！ありがとうございますした！
Thank you very much! Thank you very much!
見て、みんな！ヤゴー社長から卒業証書をもらいました！見てみて、紫咲シオンって書いてあるんだよ！
Look everyone! I received a graduation certificate from President Yagoo! Look, it says Murasaki Shion on it!
裏も！かわいい！紫咲シオンになってるー！
The back too! So cute! It's all Murasaki Shion!
ヤゴーさん、本当にありがとうございました！いっぱい質問答えてもらっちゃって、ありがとうございました！
Yagoo-san, thank you so much! Thank you for answering so many of my questions!
え、で、見てー！じゃーん！超綺麗なんだよ！ほら！上にね、あの、惑星とか月とかいっぱい付いてるの！
And look! Tada! It's so pretty! Look! Up top, there are planets and moons and lots of things!
しおん、の、金色が好きなんだよね！金色が好きだから、金色としおんのね、色の紫色にしてもらいました！超綺麗でしょ！
Shion likes gold! Because I like gold, I had them make it gold and Shion's signature purple! Isn't it super pretty?
で、さっきライブをやったステージにも行けちゃうんですね！行きますか！ライブバージョンのステージに、チェンジ！
And, we can even go to the stage where we just did the live performance! Shall we go? Change to the live version stage!
すっごーい！え、めちゃくちゃ綺麗！ほんとに！みかづきがね、こっちだ。綺麗！
Amazing! Wow, it's so gorgeous! Really! The crescent moon is over here. So pretty!
魔界学校なんだよ、これ！え、すごくない！？
It's a demon world school, this! Isn't that amazing!?
それでは皆さん、改めてまして、今日は紫咲シオンの卒業配信に来てくれて、本当にありがとうございました！
Everyone, once again, thank you so much for coming to Murasaki Shion's graduation stream today!
明日からはこちら！紫咲シオン卒業ライブでたくさんポストしてください！スクショ待ってます！
Starting tomorrow, it's this! Please post a lot about Murasaki Shion's graduation live! I'm waiting for your screenshots!
トレンド1位乗ってるらしいです！ありがとうございます！
Apparently we hit #1 on trending! Thank you so much!
はい、というわけで歌わせいただいた楽曲ですが、1曲目は「紫咲」、2曲目は「誰かの心臓になれたら」でした！
Yes, so the songs I had you listen to, the first was "Murasaki" and the second was "Dareka no Shinzou ni Naretara"!
みんな、どうだった？コメント、ちょっとたまに止まったりしてるんだけど、見れるかな？読みてます。
Everyone, how was it? The comments are freezing up a bit sometimes, but can I see them? I'm reading them.
見てますけど、ちょっと…
I am reading them, but...
タイムラグ、タイムラグなのかな、これは。ちょっと、固まっちゃって、うーん、めちゃくちゃ綺麗だな、あのステージね。ステージ、うん、そのみなそのステージの、あのまだ次元にいるわ。ステージの次元にいる。
Is there a time lag? It froze up. Hmm, that stage is so gorgeous. The stage... yeah, I'm still in that stage dimension. I'm in the stage dimension.
ありがとうございます、本当に！紫咲はね、あの1回歌ったことある曲なんですけど、思い入れがある曲なので一番最初に歌わせていただきました。
Thank you so much, really! "Murasaki" is a song I've sung once before, but it's a song I have a lot of attachment to, so I had it sung first.
誰かの心臓になれたらは、あの正直本当バカ高かった、高かったけど、高かったけど頑張っ、あ、見えた！コメント見えた！
As for "Dareka no Shinzou ni Naretara," honestly it was crazy high, it was high, but although it was high I did my— Ah, I see it! I can see the comments!
ずっと固まってまーすって言ってる。うん、ずっと固まってたけど動けたよ、今。今ちょうど動き出しました。うーん、コメント重いよね、やっぱみんないっぱいコメントしてくれてるから重くなっちゃうんだよね。てかめっちゃ綺麗だね、これ。これ。
You guys are saying it's been frozen the whole time. Yeah, it was frozen the whole time, but it moved now. It just started moving now. Hmm, the comments are heavy, huh? Since everyone is posting so many comments, it gets heavy. Also, this is super pretty, isn't it? This.
はい、というわけでね、みんなたくさんのコメントとたくさんのポスト、ありがとうございました本当に！
Right, so everyone, thank you so much for all the comments and posts! Really!
というわけで、このあとはゲストパートになります！最後まで見ていってね！
With that, the rest will be the guest part! Make sure to watch until the end!
今なんじゃない?
What is it now?
メラメラとたぎる
Boiling with excitement
眠っているだけの正義
Justice just sleeping
こんな僕も君のヒーローになりたいのさ
I want to be your hero too
かっこいい君には僕じゃ頼りなのかなんて
To the cool you, am I unreliable?
Mela!
今なんじゃない?
Isn't it now?
君には
To you,
ボクじゃ頼りないのかなんて
am I not reliable enough?
そりゃそうだろだって
Of course that's right, because
今もこうして迷ってる
even now I'm hesitating like this.
手を取ってくれないか
Won't you take my hand?
ギブとテイクさ
It's give and take
君が僕のヒーローだったように
just like you were my hero.
今なんじゃない? メラメラとたぎる
Isn't it now? Boiling with excitement,
こんなボクにも潜る正義が
the justice hidden even in a guy like me
どうしようもない衝動に駆られて
is driven by an irresistible impulse.
ほら気付けば手を握っている
Look, before you know it, we're holding hands.
一体ぜんたい そんなに荷物を背負い込んでどこへ行くの
Where are you going carrying so much baggage?
ねぇねぇ待って ボクにちょっと預けてみては
Hey, wait, why not entrust a little to me?
信じてばかりのボクと
With me who only believes
信じることが怖いキミと
and you who are afraid to believe,
どちらが正しいのかなんて
which one of us is right?
誰にも分からないさ
No one knows.
ボクらだけの世界
Our own world.
ギブとテイクさ
It's give and take.
補い合えた暁には同じ夢を見たい
In the dawn we share, I want to dream the same dream.
キミはかっこいいと苦しめて
You suffered, trying to be cool,
ひとりぼっちにさせたのは
and leaving you all alone
キミはかっこいいと苦しめて
You suffered, trying to be cool,
ひとりぼっちにさせたのは少し
and leaving you all alone
ボクのせいなんだよなごめんね
was a little bit my fault. I'm sorry.
だけど見るべきはリアルだ
But what you should see is reality.
今こそボクが助けるんだ
Now is the time for me to save you.
抱えないで信じて頼ってほしいんだ
Don't carry it alone, believe in me and rely on me.
今なんじゃない? メラメラとたぎる
Isn't it now? Boiling with excitement,
こんなボクにも潜る正義が
the justice hidden even in a guy like me
どうしようもない衝動に駆られて
is driven by an irresistible impulse.
ほら気付けば手を握っている
Look, before you know it, we're holding hands.
ほっとけない そんなに荷物を背負い込んでどこへ行くの
I can't leave you alone. Where are you going with all that baggage?
ほんのちょっとボクにちょっと預けてみては
Why not entrust just a little bit of it to me?
こんなボクもキミのヒーローになりたいのさ
I want to be your hero too.
星座になれたら
[Title: If I Could Be a Constellation]
もうすぐ時計は6時
The clock is almost at 6 o'clock
もうそこに一番星
and the first star is already there.
影を踏んで夜に紛れたくなる帰り道
On my way home, stepping on shadows, wanting to get lost in the night.
どんなに探してみても
No matter how much I search,
一つしかない星
there's only that one star.
何億光年離れたところからあんなに輝いて
Shining so brightly from hundreds of millions of light-years away.
いいな 君は
Must be nice, you
みんなから愛されて
are loved by everyone.
「いいや 僕は ずっと一人きりさ」
"No, I've always been all alone."
君と集まって星座になれたら
If I could get together with you and become a constellation,
星降る夜 一瞬の願い事
a fleeting wish on a starry night,
きらめいて ゆらめいて 震えているシグナル
twinkling, shimmering, quavering signal.
もうすぐ時計は6時
It's almost 6 o'clock on the clock
もうそこに一番星
The first star is already there
影を踏んで 夜に紛れたくなる帰り道
Stepping on shadows on my way home, wanting to get lost in the night
空見上げて 指をさされるような
Looking up at the sky, as if being pointed at
つないだ線 ほどかないで
Don't untie the connected lines
僕がどんなに 眩しくても
No matter how dazzling I am
もうすぐ時計は8時
It's almost 8 o'clock on the clock
夜空に満天の星
A sky full of stars in the night
何億光年 離れたところには もうないかもしれない
Billions of light-years away, it might not even be there anymore
月が綺麗で 泣きそうになるのは
The moon is so beautiful, and I feel like crying
いつの一日か 別れが来るから
Because one day, a parting will come
君と集まって 星座になれたら
If only I could gather with you and become a constellation
彗星みたい 流れるひとりごと
A soliloquy drifting like a comet
君と集まって 星座になれたら
If only I could gather with you and become a constellation
切なる願い 誰かに届いたら
If my earnest wish reaches someone
消えていく残像は 真夜中のプリズム
The afterimage that fades away is a midnight prism
君と集まって 星座になれたら
If only I could gather with you and become a constellation
切なる願い 誰かに届いたら
If my earnest wish reaches someone
変われるかな 夜の淵を なぞるような
I wonder if I could change, like tracing the edges of the night
どんな僕でも
Even a person like me
遥か彼方 僕らは出会ってしまった
We met far away in the distance
カルマだから 何度も出会ってしまおう
Because it's karma, we will meet again and again
雲の隙間で
In the gaps of the clouds
君と集まって 星座になれたら
If only I could gather with you and become a constellation
夜空広げて 描こう絵空事
Let's spread the night and draw a pipe dream
暗闇を照らすような 満月じゃなくても
Even if it's not a full moon that illuminates the darkness
だから集まって 星座になりたい
That's why I want to gather and become a constellation
色とりどの光 放つような つないだ線 解かないで
Like emitting colorful light, I won't untie the connected lines
君がどんなに眩しくても
No matter how dazzling you are
ねえ 想い出のカケラに
Hey, on a piece of memory
名前をつけて保存するなら “宝物”がぴったりだね
If you give it a name and save it, "treasure" is a perfect fit
そう ココロの容量がいっぱいになるくらいに 過ごしたね とめめき色の毎日
We spent days full of heart-throbbing color, enough to fill our hearts to the brim
なじんだ制服と上履き ホワイトボードの落書き
Worn-out school uniforms, indoor shoes, and doodles on the whiteboard
明日の入り口に 置いてかなくちゃいけないのかな
I wonder if we have to leave them behind at tomorrow's entrance
でもね、会えたよ! すてきな天使に 卒業は終わりじゃない これからも仲間だから
But hey, we met a wonderful angel! Graduation isn't the end, because we'll be friends forever
一緒の写真たち おそろいのキーホルダー
Photos of us together and matching keychains
いつまでも輝いてる ずっと その笑顔 ありがとう
They will shine forever. Thank you for that smile, always
ねえ 桜の木もちょっと 背中が伸びたみたい
Hey, the cherry blossom trees seem to have grown a bit taller
見えないゆっくりなスピードでも きっと あの空は見てたね
Even if I couldn't see the slow pace, I'm sure that sky was watching
何度もつまづいたこと それでも最後まで歩けたこと
All those times we stumbled, but still managed to walk until the end
ふわり 放課後の廊下に こぼれた音符の羽根 ふふふ積もるまで このままでいられたらいいのにな
Gently, the feathers of music fell in the hallway after school... I wish we could stay like this forever
でもね、ふれたよ! 愛すべき天使に ただいまって言いたい この場所は変わらないよ
But hey, we touched a beloved angel! I want to say "I'm home", this place will never change
メールの受信箱 まるしたカレンダー
The inbox of my emails and the circled calendar
とびきりの夢と出会わせてくれた 音楽に ありがとう
Thank you for the music that brought me wonderful dreams and encounters
駅のホーム 河原の道 離れても 同じ空 見上げて
At the station platform, on the path by the riverbed, looking up at the same sky even if apart
ユニゾンで歌おう! でもね、会えたよ! すてきな天使に 卒業は終わりじゃない
Let's sing in unison! But hey, we met a wonderful angel! Graduation isn't the end
これからも仲間だから 大好き って言うなら だいだいい大好きって返すよ
Because we'll be friends from here on out. If you say "I love you", we'll say "We love you so much more!"
忘れ物 もうないよね ずっと 永遠に一緒だよ
There's nothing left to forget. We'll be together for eternity
ねぇ思い出のカケラに
Hey, if I could just put a name
名前をつけて保存するなら
to these fragments of memories,
“宝物”がぴったりだね
"treasure" fits them best.
そうココロの容量がいっぱいになるくらいに 過ごしたねときめき色の毎日
Yeah, we spent our thrilling, colorful days until our hearts were overflowing.
なじんだ制服と上履き
Our familiar uniforms and indoor shoes,
ホワイトボードの落書き
and doodles on the whiteboard—
明日の入り口に置いてこなくちゃいけないのかな
I wonder if we have to leave them at tomorrow's entrance?
でもね会えたよ すてきな天使に
But hey, I met a wonderful angel!
卒業は終わりじゃない これからも仲間だから
Graduation isn't the end, we're still friends from here on out.
一緒の写真たち おそろいのキーホルダー
All our photos together, matching keychains—
いつまでも輝いている ずっと思い出ありがとう
they'll shine forever. Thank you for all the memories.
ねぇ桜の木もちょっと背中が伸びたみたい
Hey, the cherry blossom trees seem to have grown a bit taller too.
見えないゆっくりなスピードでもきっとあの空は見てたね
Even at an invisible, slow pace, I'm sure that sky was watching.
何度もつまづいたこと それでも最後まで歩けたこと
All those times we stumbled, yet managed to walk until the very end.
ふわり放課後の廊下に こぼれた音符の羽根
Gently, in the hallway after school, fell the feathers of a musical note.
ふかふか積もるまで このままでいれたらいいのにね
If only they could pile up softly and stay like this forever.
でもね触れたよ 愛すべき天使に
But hey, I touched a beloved angel!
ただいまっていいたくなる この場所は変わらないよ
Making me want to say "I'm home"—this place will never change.
メールの受信箱 まるしたカレンダー
The inbox for emails, the circled calendar—
とびきりの夢と出会わせてくれた 音楽にありがとう
thank you to the music that brought us such extraordinary dreams.
駅のホーム 河原の道 離れてても同じ空見上げ
On the station platform, the path by the river, even when apart, we look up at the same sky.
ユニゾンで歌おう
Let's sing in unison!
でもね会えたよ すてきな天使に
But hey, I met a wonderful angel!
卒業は終わりじゃない これからも仲間だから
Graduation isn't the end, we're still friends from here on out.
大好きっていうなら だいだい大好きって返すよ
If you say "I love you," I'll reply with "I love you so, so much!"
忘れ物もないよね ずっと永遠に一緒だよ
There's nothing left behind, we'll be together forever.
ねぇ思い出のカケラに
Hey, if I could just put a name
名前をつけて保存するなら
to these fragments of memories,
“宝物”がぴったりだね
"treasure" fits them best.
そうココロの容量がいっぱいになるくらいに 過ごしたねときめき色の毎日
Yeah, we spent our thrilling, colorful days until our hearts were overflowing.
でもね会えたよ すてきな天使に
But hey, I met a wonderful angel!
卒業は終わりじゃない これからも仲間だから
Graduation isn't the end, we're still friends from here on out.
大好きっていうなら だいだい大好きって返すよ
If you say "I love you," I'll reply with "I love you so, so much!"
忘れ物もないよね ずっと永遠に一緒だよ
There's nothing left behind, we'll be together forever.
駅のホーム 河原の道 離れてても同じ空見上げ
On the station platform, the path by the river, even when apart, we look up at the same sky.
ユニゾンで歌おう
Let's sing in unison!
でもね会えたよ すてきな天使に
But hey, I met a wonderful angel!
ずっと永遠に一緒だよ
We'll be together forever.
いつもモノクロだった瞳の奥の景色すてたら夢見つけた
By getting rid of the monochrome landscapes in the back of my eyes, I found my dream.
何もない世界で創る絆は強い意志あたえた
This bond created in a completely empty world gave us a strong will.
裏返した日常でまた走っていく先に君はいた
Within the everyday, upside down, I continued to run, and you were at the end.
触れた心は輝いた鮮やかな色になって羽ばたくよ希望乗せて
My heart shone and took on vivid colors after you touched it; it will fly, carrying hope.
無限に広がる空の下集まった願い守り進めば
If I protect the wishes gathered under the sky that extends to infinity and advance—
まだ誰も知らない明日へと
toward a tomorrow still unknown to all.
引き寄せられるように覗いた瞬間光の糸は君包んだ
At the moment I peeked as if drawn in, threads of light wrapped around you.
細く千切れそうな絡まった運命きっとまだ変えられる
Our tangled destinies, thin and ready to snap, can surely still change.
間違いでも信じた道は新しい景色を照らすだろう
Even if I made a mistake, the path I believed in will surely illuminate new landscapes.
巡る時間の中笑って様々な思い持って始めようまた一から
Inside the cycle of time, we laughed and felt different feelings; let's start again from the beginning.
たどり着いた僅かな奇跡壊れないように手を伸ばしつなげば
If I reach out my hand so the ephemeral miracle we arrived at won't break—
無限に広がる空の下集まった願い守りゆけば
If I continue to protect the wishes gathered under the sky that extends to infinity,
まだ透明な私たちはどんな色にでも染まることができるから夢叶えよう
We are still transparent and can take on any color, so let's make our dreams come true!
走っていく先に君はいた
I continued to run, and you were at the end.
触れた心は輝いた鮮やかな色になって羽ばたくよ希望乗せて
My heart shone and took on vivid colors after you touched it; it will fly, carrying hope.
無限に広がる空の下集まった願い守りゆけば
If I continue to protect the wishes gathered under the sky that extends to infinity,
君と誓ったあの日の記憶 今越えて過去からまだ誰も知らない明日へと
I will be able to overcome the memories of the day I made an oath with you and leave from the past toward a tomorrow still unknown to all.
新しい景色を
Illuminating a new scenery...
照らすだろう
will surely light it up.
巡る
Revolving
時の中
in the flow of time,
笑って 様々な想い持って
smiling, carrying various feelings,
始めよう
let's begin
また一から
once more from scratch.
辿り着いた儚い奇跡 壊れないように
So that the fleeting miracle we reached won't break,
手を伸ばし 繋げばほら
if we reach out and connect our hands, look,
ほら 君は側で いつまでも...
you are by my side, forever...
まだ透明な 私たちは
We are still transparent,
どんな色にでも 染まることができるから
so we can be dyed in any color we choose.
夢叶えよう
Let's make our dreams come true.
走って行く先に
Ahead of where we're running,
君はいた
you were there.
触れた 心は輝いた
When we touched, our hearts shone brightly.
鮮やかな色になって 羽ばたくよ
Turning into vivid colors, taking flight,
希望乗せて 無限に広がる
carrying hope across the infinitely expanding
空の下 集まった願い守り行けば
sky beneath us, if we protect our gathered wishes and go forward,
君と誓った あの日の記憶
the memories of that day we swore to each other
今超えて
now transcend the past
過去から まだ誰も知らない 明日へと
and head toward a tomorrow unknown to anyone yet.
はーい！というわけで、ぺこらちゃんに来てもらいました！
Hii! So, we invited Pekora-chan to join us!
来ました、ぺこちゃーーん！
I'm here, Peko-chaaan!
卒業するかい！？
You're graduating?!
ぺこちゃん来てくれてありがとう！卒業ライブに！
Pekora-chan, thank you for coming to my graduation live!
いやいやいや、むしろ呼んでくれてありがとうぺこだけど。
No, no, no, thank you so much for inviting me, Peko.
ありがとう！一緒にカラオケ歌えて、めっちゃ嬉しかった！
Thank you! I was so happy we got to sing karaoke together!
え、そう、終わったの？
Eh, wait, it's already over?
窓際の曲じゃん！え、二人で歌う曲だなと思って、え、ふぺこちゃんの声に絶対合うと思ったわけよ。
I thought it's a song for two people to sing, and I knew it would definitely suit Peko-chan's voice!
あー！はー！はー！そ！だから一緒に歌いたいなと思って、え、もういいし。
Right! That's why I wanted us to sing it together, so... yeah!
あ、じゃあ二人は、え、魔法少女ってこと？
Oh, so the two of you are... magical girls?
そういうこと！あ、じゃあ今日、
That's right! Oh, so today—
我らは、え、てんか統一…うちら二人！ あれ、一緒じゃん！
We are... conquering the world... the two of us! Wait, that's the same!
いや、一緒じゃねえし、あれ魔法少女じゃねえし！
No, that's not the same at all, and that's not magical girls!
やめてよ、なんか魔法少女の話してたのに急にさ…
Stop it, we were talking about magical girls and suddenly...
いや、今、急に行ったら覚えてるのかなっていうので、え、そう。かわいいことね！
Well, I wondered if you'd remember if I brought it up suddenly, so yeah. How cute!
なんだ、ちゃんと覚えてるじゃん！てんか統一、うちら二人の下り。あれ、でも、そうだったんだ！そういう選曲だったんだね！
What, you remembered properly! The whole "conquering the world, just the two of us" bit. Oh, so that was it! That's why you chose that song!
窓際の曲で、カラオケ歌いたいなっていう…お！
You wanted to sing "Windowside" at karaoke together, huh? Oh!
もうなんか、途中でね、ぺこちゃんと最初に歌ってて、ぺこちゃんがさ、窓が見えてきたの！
And you know, halfway through, while singing with Peko-chan at the start, I started seeing the window!
マジで言ってる？え、でも待って、窓描くかもって思って…
Are you serious? Eh, but wait, I thought "maybe I'll draw a window..."
え、可愛い！窓描くかもって思ってきた！
Eh, cute! You thought "maybe I'll draw a window"!
ってことは、あ、けみほむら？
That means... ah, Akemi Homura?
はい。なんか見えてきちゃったかも、救いたい！
Yes. Somehow it felt like I could see her, I want to save her!
あ、ぺこらを救いたい！ぺこらを救いたい！救いたい！
Ah, I want to save Pekora! I want to save Pekora! Save her!
世界線に…世界線にしたい！シオンは何度も、死んで、
I want to make it a worldline where... I want to save Pekora across worldlines! Shion died so many times...
ぺこらを救うんだ！まじかよ、なんか、話逆じゃないの、なんか？
...to save Pekora! Seriously? Wait, isn't that backwards, or something?
え、なんかさ、今までさ、天香統一の話ばっかりしてたじゃん！
Eh, like, until now, we've only been talking about conquering the world!
それは、おろすぎるな、マジで！
That's way too dumb, seriously!
え、なんかさ、今までさ、天香統一かと思って…キッズだったと思って…
Eh, like, until now, I thought it was about conquering the world... I thought it was for kids...
天香統一ってさ、キッズやったと思って！天香統一って結構最近！
I thought "conquering the world" was for kids! "Conquering the world" is actually pretty recent!
え、そう、最近だよ！だってみんなさ、ぺこらたちって、おつこらぼとかって、もう5、6年前とかじゃない？ ちょっと離してたけどさ、マリオカート！
Eh, yeah, it's recent! I mean, everyone, us Pekoras, like, otukorabo and stuff was already 5 or 6 years ago, right? We drifted apart a bit, but Mario Kart!
ありました！
There was!
あのときのペこちゃんはなんてウイウイしくて可愛かったんでしょう。
Back then, how innocent and cute Pekora-chan was.
今は？ 今も可愛いよね。
What about now? She's still cute, right?
きのこのきのこ取れなかったペこ。
Pekora couldn't get the mushroom, peko.
やめてペこ！ ペこ、うわ、落ちたペこ！
Stop it, peko! Peko, oh, Peko fell!
え、そう思ったらしょんちゃんってマジ変わんないかも。
Come to think of it, Shion-chan might not have changed at all.
え、マジで？
Seriously?
え、最初から今まで？ え、なんかっていうか
From the very beginning until now? Well, like...
え、最初からクソガキだし。
Well, you've been a brat from the very start.
でも何回かやっぱ遊ぶたびにクソガキ感もありつつもう大人な部分もちゃんとするんだなっていうのは
But still, every time we hung out, while keeping that bratty vibe, I realized you also have a mature side...
え、ずっと持ってたよね？
Wait, you thought that all along?
うん、ずっと持っててくれた。
Yeah, I thought that the whole time.
そう、でもペこちゃんワン時はペこ、あー落ちたペこ！わあ、しょせーい！
Yeah, but Pekora-chan, back then, Peko, ah, Peko fell! Wow, so fresh!
まあ、あの時もほら、一生懸命尻尾ペコらでしょんちゃんって呼んでって一生懸命続けたらしょんちゃんって呼んでくれるようになった。
Well, back then too, see, when I kept trying to call you "Shion-chan" with all my might, you started calling me "Shion-chan."
いや、確かにペこら結構先輩とかにはさ、先輩って言いたいペこだからの。
Yeah, that's true, Pekora usually likes to call seniors "senpai," you know.
でもね、やっぱ、もう今は言い慣れたしょんちゃんとかってですごい言い慣れたペこだけど、やっぱ最初のその先輩からしょんちゃんって呼び方を変えるときはめっちゃんこ大変だった。
But you know, now I'm used to saying "Shion-chan" and stuff, but at first, changing how I addressed you from "senpai" to "Shion-chan" was super tough.
うん、なんか頑張ってんだろうなっていうのが、めっちゃんこ頑張ってるんだろうなってのがちょっと伝わってきて、なんかちょ申し訳ないなって思ってたんだけど、なんか乗り越えてくれた。
Yeah, I felt like you were working hard on it, and that really came across, and I felt a bit bad about it, but you overcame it.
うん、頑張りよ乗り越えてしょんちゃん定着したから。
Yeah, and after pushing through that, "Shion-chan" became our thing.
いや、そう、もうこれからもね。
Yeah, and from now on too.
そうだね、最近でもね、天下統一活動してきて、今や、今もね、天下統一活動して
That's right. Recently too, we've been doing unification activities, and even now, we're doing unification activities—
そうだよ、天下統一開催しないからね。え、そうだよ、あのしょんちゃんが卒業したとしても天下統一はえー
That's right, we're holding the unification event! Wait, even if Shion-chan graduates, the unification—
あのずっと永久活動中だから天下統一は統一していくからこれからもね。
We've been in permanent activity, so the unification will keep going from now on too.
これからもね、うん、最近もね色々天下統一してきたよね。
From now on too, yeah, and recently we've done all sorts of unification stuff, right?
なんだったっけ？
What was it again?
なんだっけなんだっけじゃねえよ！なんかねえのかよ！1つくらい。
What was it, what was it? Don't give me that! Isn't there anything? At least one!
もうはやとね！そうだよ、はやとね！
Oh, Hayato-ne! That's right, Hayato-ne!
あとは？ あとはカラオケ行ったね。
What else? We went to karaoke.
え、それそれ、それめっちゃ前じゃん。
Ah, right, that was ages ago!
今や！ 今さっきやんもう！
Now! That was just a moment ago!
確かにでも色々、でも確かにライブとかでいっぱい歌ったもんな。そうだよな、ライブとかでもいっぱい歌ったし、ペこらたち結構さ、結構活動してきこたよ。
True, but we sang a lot at lives and stuff. That's true, we sang a lot at lives, and Pekora and I have quite... We've been active for quite a while.
5年前だよ、初コラボ。
5 years ago was our first collab.
5年、え？
5 years, huh?
5年？ え、何年デビューして？ 6年目？
5 years? How many years since debut? 6th year?
今6年目？ 7年目なんだよ。
6th year? It's our 7th year.
長い！ 長い！ マジで言ってる？
So long! So long! Are you serious?
そうなのよ。
That's right.
長いよね。
It's long, isn't it?
長いけどさ、ペこら今日しょんちゃんに伝えたいことがある。何？
It is long, but, Peko-chan, today there's something I want to tell Shion-chan. What is it?
ちょっと待ってて。
Wait a second.
え、何？
Eh, what?
ペこら！
Pekora!
まじで？
Seriously?
今日、うわ、待って！しょんちゃんと、しょんちゃんが今日卒業してしまうということで、手紙を書いてきたペこ。
Today... whoa, wait! Since Shion-chan is graduating today, Peko wrote a letter.
びっくりしたでしょ。びっくりした！ガチで知らなかったでしょ。
Were you surprised? I was surprised! You seriously didn't know, right?
しかもガチで書いてる。
And you wrote it for real!
見ないで。え、マジで知らなかった。嘘。
Hey, don't look. Seriously, I didn't know. No way.
じゃあ、ちょっと読ませてもらいます。
Well then, please let me read it.
しょんちゃんへ
Dear Shion-chan,
はい。
Yes.
ヤッホー。もう卒業か。
Yoo-hoo. Graduating already?
ヤッホー。
Yoo-hoo.
許すそれ。寂しいよ。なんでやめちゃうんだよって言っても困らせるだけだとう思うので、ペこらがしょんちゃんに思っていることを伝えようと思います。
Forgive me for that. I'm lonely. Even if I say "Why are you quitting?", I think that would only trouble you, so I wanted to share what I feel toward Shion-chan.
え？うん。
Yeah. Yeah.
しょんちゃんと初めてコミュニケーションを取ったのはペこらがホロライブに入ったときにしょんちゃんからディスコで声をかけてくれたのが最初だったよね。びっくりしたね。
The first time Shion-chan and I communicated was when Pekora joined Hololive, and Shion-chan reached out to me on Discord. That was our beginning. I was surprised.
ペこらは人見知りすごかったから先輩から声をかけてもらえることがとても嬉しかったペこ。よかった。
Pekora was super shy, so I was so happy that a senior reached out to me, peko. I'm glad.
そこからいろいろなコラボをして子供っぽいところもありつつしっかりと大人な部分もあるし、先輩なのに話しやすいし遊んでて楽しい、そして何より優しいしょんちゃんが大好きです。
From there, we did various collabs, and while there were childish parts, you also had a proper adult side. Even though you were a senior, you were easy to talk to and fun to hang out with. Above all, I love kind Shion-chan.
うん。ありがとう。
Yeah. Thank you.
もう恥ずかしいな。
How embarrassing.
ありがとう。
Thank you.
いや2人旅もしょんちゃんだから行けたんだと思う。知らなかったクレーンゲームのうまさや気をつかうところ、ここでは話せないこともたくさん話せた旅行だった。
I think I was only able to go on our two-person trip because it was with Shion-chan. It was a trip where we talked about so many things we couldn't talk about here—like your unexpected skill at crane games and how considerate you are.
うん、たくさん話したね。今度はどこへ行こうか。
Yeah, we talked a lot. Where should we go next?
正直卒業すると聞いたときはびっくりしつつもどこか腑に落ちる自分もいて、残り少ない時間でたくさんの思い出を一緒に作りたいなと思いました。
Honestly, when I heard you were graduating, while being surprised, part of me also understood, and I thought I wanted to make so many memories together in the remaining time.
作れたかな？作れたよ。作れたよね。たくさん天下統一したもん。
Were we able to make them? We were able to. We made them, didn't we? We achieved a lot of unification.
卒業はとても寂しいし悲しいけど
Graduation is so lonely and sad, but...
ペこらとしょんちゃんの関係は
The bond between Pekora and Shion-chan...
ありません！
No, thank you!
てぇてぇコラボは永久不滅！
Let's make this collab eternal!
はい。
Yeah.
それでは本当に最後の挨拶をしますよ！
Now, let's do the final greeting!
はい！
Yeah!
わためぇ！
Everyone!
てぇてぇコラボ！
Forever collab!
うじたっとりー！
Ujitatori!
しおん大好きだぞ！
Shion, we love you so much!
ありがとー！びっくりしたー！
Thank you so much!
じゃあ、まだ多分この後も卒業ライブがあると思うから。
Well, I bet there's more live streams after this too, so.
頑張ってね。
Do your best.
ねえ、ありがとー。
Yeah, thank you.
これあとで渡すから。
I'll give this to you later.
え？
Eh?
ゆみまっさとで、ありがとぜったー！
Yumimasso-to-de, thank you so much!
ありがと！
Thank you!
ゆみまっさとー！
Yumimasso!
ありがとー！
Thank you!
まぢかよ。
Wait, what?
気分次第です僕は 敵を選んで戦う少年
Depending on my mood, I'm a boy who picks out his enemies to fight,
叶えない未来もなくて 夢に描かれるのを待ってた
with no hopes for the future, waiting to be drawn in a dream.
そのくせ未来が怖くて 明日を嫌って過去に願って
And yet I fear the future, hating tomorrow, wishing towards the past,
もう何処そうもなくなって叫ぶんだ
shouting because there's no longer anything I can do.
明日よ明日よもう来ないでよってそんな
"Tomorrow, please don't come," I say.
僕を置いて 月は沈み陽は昇る
Leaving me behind, the moon sets and the sun rises.
だけどその夜は違ったんだ 君は僕の手を
But that night was different, you took my hand—
空へ舞う世界の彼方 闇を照らす凱旋いぇーえー
Dancing into the sky and beyond this world, the Big Dipper illuminates the darkness.
君と僕もさ また明日へ向かっていこう
"Let's start facing towards tomorrow again, both you and me."
夢で終わってしまうのなら昨日を変えさせて
"If this is to end as a dream, let's change yesterday,"
なんて言わないから
I won't say anything like that.
また明日も君とこうやって笑わせて
So let me keep smiling together with you, tomorrow as well.
あれから世界は変わってだって 本気で思ったって
Even if I think that the world truly changed,
期待したって変えようとしたって 未来は残酷で
and even if I tried to hope or change, the future was cruel.
それでもいつだって君と見ていた 世界は本当に綺麗だった
Even so, the world I always watched with you was truly beautiful—
忘れてないさ 思い出せるように仕舞ってんの
I haven't forgotten that, I've placed it in my heart so I can remember.
君がいてもいなくても翔べるなんて妄想
Daydreaming about flying with or without you,
独りで歩くことさえ僕は
or even just taking a walk alone,
しないまま藍色の風に吐いた幻想
I begged for someone to break down the illusions formed from the indigo wind.
壊してくれてって願ってもがいたって ああ
"If you want it, then make it come true yourself," you said.
願ったんなら叶えてしまえやって
君は言っていた
I'm thinking that I want to go see you again tomorrow night,
また明日の夜に 逢いに行こうと思うがどうかな君はないかな
but I don't know, maybe you won't be there.
それでもいつまでも僕ら一つだから またね Sky Arrow 笑ってよう
So, see you later, Sky Arrow, let's smile on.
未来を少しでも君といたいから 叫ぼう 今日の日をいつか思い出せ 未来の僕ら
I want to be together with you in the future, however short our time may be.
はーい！
Ha-i!
ということでね。
So, yeah.
いやー次のゲストなんですが。
Yeah, um, for the next guest,
ちょっとハードルが高そうなんだよねー。
hm, the hurdle sounds pretty high, doesn't it?
めちゃくちゃ厄介な魔法所には 召喚される人が喜ぶものを捧げると
It says that if you offer something that the person being summoned would be happy about,
成功するって書いてあったんだけど……
it'll succeed, but...
やるしかない。
Well, I guess I have no choice.
磨いとかこ。
I gotta brush.
磨いて磨いて。
Gotta brush, brush, brush.
よし。
Alright.
はーい！
Ha-i!
うおっ、出てこいっ！
Whoa, come out!
うおー！
Whoa!
うわー！
えー、シオン先輩！
Eh, Shion-senpai!
で、できた、本当にできた！
It-it worked, it really worked!
待って待って！
Wait, wait!
足が、待って！
My legs, wait!
本当にできた？
It really worked?
待って、足が！
Wait, my legs!
待って、足が、うわ、足が、足が！
Wait, my legs, whoa, my legs, my legs!
待って、入ってきた！
Wait, they're coming in!
入ってきたほうが、思ってたのと違うかも。
Coming in... might be different from what I thought.
もうすぐお尻に届きそう。
It's almost reaching my butt.
キモい！
Gross!
キモすぎる！
So gross!
逃げないで、逃げないで！
Don't run away, don't run away!
えっ？
Eh?
本当に……本当にさ、
Really... really,
うーん、ちょっとよく見せて、ちょっと。
hmm, let me see closely, a bit.
あ、はい、どうぞ。
Ah, yes, go ahead.
ちょっと立って立って立って。
Hold on, stand up, stand up, stand up.
えっ？
Eh?
じゃあ……
Well then...
うまーい。
So skillful.
あとで全部見せてあげるのに。
Even though I'll show you everything later.
なんです、なんです？
What is it, what is it?
どこが？
Where?
あ、でも逆マッタ。
Ah, but it's inverted.
これ、これは本当に逆マッタ。
This, this is really inverted.
見た目は逆マッタっぽいよね。
It looks like it's inverted, right?
もちろん！
Of course!
ちょっと、キモすぎるか。
Wait, is it too gross?
でも、いや、いや、いや、いや。
But, no, no, no, no.
失敗した可能性があるな、これ。
There's a possibility I failed, this.
お尻ですか？
My butt?
逆マッタを、えっ？
Inverted, eh?
逆マッタはこんなもんですよ。
Inverted is like this, you know.
何言った？
What did you say?
何を夢を抱いてるんですか？
What kind of dreams are you harboring?
キモかったか。
Was it gross?
え、そう、そうよね？
Eh, right, right?
そうですよね。
That's right.
足からキモかったか。
Was it gross from the feet?
うん、そこなんだ、じゃあ。
Yeah, that's it then.
そこ、久しぶりだ！
There, it's been a while!
久しぶりです！
It's been a while!
元気してた？
Have you been well?
会いたかったから呼んでくれたんですよね？
You called me because you wanted to see me, right?
えっ、そ、うまうまうま、そう。
Eh, y- yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
そこ会いたかったみたいで。
It seems you wanted to see me.
そうだよ、そう。
That's right, yeah.
会いたかったよ。
I wanted to see you.
そこもとめちゃめちゃ人気もらいました。
That person got super popular too.
あの歯ブラシこれからも使えますので。
That toothbrush can still be used from now on.
えっ、そこなんで歯ブラシで召喚されたの？
Eh, why were you summoned with a toothbrush?
いや、多分なんですけど、
Well, probably,
シオン先輩の匂いがしたと思ったからここにいたので。
because I thought I smelled Shion-senpai, so I was here.
やっぱり本能……かなと。
As expected... instinct, I guess.
あー、はい。
Ah, yes.
え、あ、匂いしたんだ、歯ブラシから。
Eh, ah, you smelled it from the toothbrush.
あ、しました、しました！
Ah, I did, I did!
さーーすっがっ、さかった。
As expected, Sakatta.
いやもう最高ですよ。
No, it's the best.
口開けていただけたら鼻突っ込みますから、全然。
If you open your mouth, I'll stick my nose in, totally.
最悪だ！
That's the worst!
キモいな！
So gross!
今日もキモさ増しましたね！
Your grossness increased even more today!
いや、でも卒業の、ね？
Well, but graduation, you know?
坂道のね、卒業ライブのときもね、
Even during Sakamichi's graduation live,
結構キモいお便りおっぱいされた……いっぱいされたんだけど、
I got a lot of gross letters... a whole lot, but
最高でしたね、あれはあれで。
it was the best, each in its own way.
うん、変わらない、変わらない感じがして、うん、よかった本当。
Yeah, it felt unchanged, yeah, I'm really glad.
よかった、変わらない感じでね。
I'm glad, keeping that unchanging vibe.
そう言われた。
That's what was said.
シンプルにしじっちゃった。
Simply shriveled up.
なんで、歌ったでも、坂道も元気そうでよかったよ、シオン本当に。
Why, you sang, but Sakamichi looked well too, I'm really glad, Shion.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
呼んでくれてよかったよ、シオン本当に。
I'm really glad you invited me, Shion.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
呼んでくれてよかった。
I'm glad you invited me.
ということで、ありがとうございました。
With that said, thank you very much.
ちょっと待って。
Wait a minute.
せっかく来てくれたんだから、
Since you specially came,
そうそう、なんだっけ、えっ？
yeah, yeah, what was it, eh?
ここもこれでいってこと？
You mean this is fine too?
え、いや、嬉しいですよ。
Eh, no, I'm happy.
また呼んでください。
Please invite me again.
待って待って待って、口隠したとかで。
Wait, wait, wait, like hiding your mouth or something.
また、またって何？またって。
Again, what do you mean by "again"?
シオン卒業する時だけど。
Even though Shion is graduating.
えっ、じゃあ、今日も、待って、待ってないよ。
Eh, well then, today too, wait, I'm not waiting.
待ってないよ、待ってないんだけど、いや、ね、ちょっと。
I'm not waiting, I'm not waiting, but, well, you know, a bit.
せっかく来てくれたんだから、
Since you specially came,
一緒に歌おうよ。
let's sing together.
もうちょっと、なんかこう……
A bit more, like this...
本当に、あの、切迫詰まる感じで。
truly, um, in a desperate sort of way.
一緒に、一緒がいいって、一緒じゃなきゃやだってみんなが言ってるからさ。
Like, together, together is good, if we're not together I don't want it, everyone is saying.
言ってくれるんです。
They tell me.
だから、なんでだろうな。
So, I wonder why.
あ、坂道の卒業ライブのとき、シオン結構あの、頑張ったと思うんだけど。
Ah, during Sakamichi's graduation live, I think Shion worked pretty hard, though.
えー！
Eh!
シオン先輩、楽しかったですよ、あれは。
Shion-senpai, it was fun, that was.
ああ、待って待って、坂道、坂道！一緒がいい！
Ah, wait wait, Sakamichi, Sakamichi! Together is better!
よし、きた！行きますか！
Alright, it's here! Shall we go?
そ、そんで、歌おう、歌ってくれるって、歌いますか！
S- so then, let's sing, you said you'd sing, shall we sing!
ということでね。
With that said.
はい、それでは聞いてください。
Yes, then please listen.
スパークル！
Sparkle!
まだこの世界は 僕を飼いならしたいみたいだ
Seems like the world's still trying to tame me
望み通りいいだろう 美しくもがくよ
If that's the way I will obey, beautifully struggle every day
お互いの砂時計 眺めながらキスをしようよ
While seeing both of our hourglasses, let's have a little kiss
「さよなら」から一番 遠い 場所で待ち合わせようよ
Let's make a plan and meet somewhere that is the most far from 'goodbye'
ついに時はきた
Finally the time has come
昨日までは序章の序章で
Everything up to yesterday was a prologue
「飛び乗りで見いだから」
Let's take short cuts instead,
ここからが僕だよ
From here on out, it's me and you.
経験と知識と
With experience and knowledge,
カビの生えかかった勇気を持って
and the courage that started to gather mold,
今だかつてないスピードで 君のもとへダイブを
I'll dive right into you at an unprecedented speed!
まどろみの中で 生温いコーラに
Inside a hazy, lukewarm can of cola,
ここでないどこかを 夢見たよ
I dreamed of somewhere outside of this world.
教室の窓の外に 電車に揺られ 運ばれる朝に
Outside the classroom window, on mornings carried by trains,
愛し方さえも 君の匂いがした
even the way you loved had your scent,
歩き方さえも その笑い声がした
even the way you walked had your laughter.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を 伸ばそうとも届かない
Words like "fate" or "future"—no matter how far they reach out their hands,
場所で僕ら恋をする
in a place where we fall in love.
時計の針も二人を 横目に見ながら進む
Even as the clock hands look sideways at us, we keep moving forward.
こんな世界を二人で 一生、いや、何章でも 生き抜いていこう
We'll live through this world—no, through any chapter—together for a lifetime!
「はじめまして」なんてさ 遥か彼方へと追いやって
"Nice to meet you," saying that to far-off tomorrows,
1000年周期を 一日で息しよう
let's breathe through a thousand-year cycle in a single day.
僕ら遊ぼうか
We'll play together.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を 伸ばそうとも届かない
Words like "fate" or "future"—no matter how far they reach out their hands,
場所で僕ら恋をする
in a place where we fall in love.
時計の針も二人を 横目に見ながら進む
Even as the clock hands look sideways at us, we keep moving forward.
こんな世界を二人で 一生、いや、何章でも 生き抜いていこう
We'll live through this world—no, through any chapter—together for a lifetime!
「はじめまして」なんてさ 遥か彼方へと追いやって
"Nice to meet you," saying that to far-off tomorrows,
1000年周期を 一日で息しよう
let's breathe through a thousand-year cycle in a single day.
僕ら遊ぼうか
We'll play together.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を 伸ばそうとも届かない
Words like "fate" or "future"—no matter how far they reach out their hands,
場所で僕ら恋をする
in a place where we fall in love.
時計の針も二人を 横目に見ながら進む
Even as the clock hands look sideways at us, we keep moving forward.
こんな世界を二人で 一生、いや、何章でも 生き抜いていこう
We'll live through this world—no, through any chapter—together for a lifetime!
「はじめまして」なんてさ 遥か彼方へと追いやって
"Nice to meet you," saying that to far-off tomorrows,
1000年周期を 一日で息しよう
let's breathe through a thousand-year cycle in a single day.
僕ら遊ぼうか
We'll play together.
運命だとか未来とかって 言葉がどれだけ手を 伸ばそうとも届かない
Words like "fate" or "future"—no matter how far they reach out their hands,
場所で僕ら恋をする
in a place where we fall in love.
時計の針も二人を 横目に見ながら進む
Even as the clock hands look sideways at us, we keep moving forward.
こんな世界を二人で 一生、いや、何章でも 生き抜いていこう
We'll live through this world—no, through any chapter—together for a lifetime!
答えて、ねぇ
Answer me, hey...
にわか雨が寄せる街の夜へ
To the night in the city where the passing rain gathers
沈む世界 感覚遡行
Submerged world, sense regression
「きっと僕ら生まれながら 何処にもないコタエを探してる」
\"We, who were born surely, are searching for an 'answer' that exists nowhere\"
答えて、ねぇ
Answer me, hey...
叶えて、何を？
Fulfill... What?
「今日の世界はいかがですか？」きっと思われずとも君は
\"How is the world today?\" Surely even without being told, you...
君を知っているだろうとも だけどまだ信じられないだろう
Know yourself, even if you are, but you still cannot believe it, right
終わる日々の果て 泣き出した想いの彼方
At the end of the days that end, beyond the thoughts that started crying
終わらない善と悪の祭典
A never-ending festival of good and evil
「なんてざま 期待も無いな」って君は君を掻き消した
\"What a pathetic sight, there's not even any expectation,\" that said, you erased yourself
時の流れに希望さえも描けない世界で
In a world where you cannot even draw hope in the flow of time
正しさなんて誰にもわからないから君は何を願ってもいいの
Since no one knows what is right, it's okay for you to wish for anything...
いいの コタエは？ 無いよ...
It's okay. Is there an answer? There is none...
「僕のことなどきっと僕はまだ」
\"Someone like me surely still...\"
悲しさのみ木霊する 孤独の中遠く浮かぶ昨日は
Only sadness echoes, yesterday floating far away in loneliness
「今日で世界は終わります」君が拒めど此の暮れに咲かせ死に花
\"The world will end today\" even if you refuse, in this dusk a death flower blooms
成るは厭なり想うは成らず 君の全てはね
Things do not go well, thoughts do not come true, this is everything about you, isn't it
止まない憂いの最中 二つ感情は対を成して願いを放つ
In the midst of unceasing sorrow, two emotions pair up and release a wish
君は覚えているかな あの日涙の意味を
Do you remember the meaning of the tears that day?
この世はまだ終わらない 明けぬ夜が今日を塞いでたって僕は歌う「嫌いじゃないな」って
This world is not over yet, even if the dawnless night blocks today, I will sing, \"I don't hate this\"
さあ暗い空が晴れる 泣きやんだ今日にさらば
Come on, the dark sky will clear up, farewell to today, when you stopped crying
変わらない想いを振り翳すように生きていく 泣きながらでいいさ
I will live as if to hold up this unchanging feeling, it's okay to cry
それを繰り返して笑える生きていく また明日の雨に打たれたって
A life where you can smile after repeating that, even if I'm struck by tomorrow's rain
いつかこの世に生まれてきてよかったって言えるようになるかな その日まで
Someday, I was born into this world, I wonder if I will be able to say \"I'm glad\"
負けないよ 負けないよ
I will not give up... I will not give up...
続く時間の欠片を 集めている ただ
I am only collecting fragments of the time that passes by endlessly
過ぎるノートの余白に書く 「答えは、いつ？」
I write in the margins of my notebook, \"When will the answer come?\"
過ぎるノートの
Passing notes...
「答えは、いつ？」
"When is the answer?"
ほんのり小さな感情へ
To a tiny, gentle emotion...
愛をひとつ またね またね
A single love, see you again, see you again.
夜に咲く温度と灯るまで
Until the warmth blooms into the night and lights up.
呼吸ひとつ 生きる 生きる
A single breath, living, living,
優しい日々の横で泣かぬように ああ
so I won't cry beside these gentle days.
ちっちゃな言葉 チクチクしたの キリが無いけどさ
Prickling little words don't have an end,
それを忘れたフリ 疲れたよ
but I'm tired of pretending to forget it.
夜よ抱きしめて
Night, hold me close.
今日だって 笑う 笑う
Even today, I laugh and laugh,
泣いちゃう僕を隠すために笑う
laughing to hide the crying me.
って思えたら軽くなれるのかな
Would it feel lighter if I thought so?
愛をひとつ またね またね
A single love, see you again, see you again.
夜に咲く温度と灯るまで
Until the warmth blooms into the night and lights up.
呼吸ひとつ 生きる 生きる
A single breath, living, living,
優しい日々の横で泣かぬように
so I won't cry beside these gentle days.
愛をひとつ またね またね
A single love, see you again, see you again.
優しい日々の横で笑うように
As I smile beside these gentle days.
吐き出す気持ちは簡単で
The feeling of letting go is easy,
でも生きるの難易度高すぎて どうにも解けない問いだらけ
but living is too hard, filled with unanswerable questions.
愛をひとつ またね またね
A single love, see you again, see you again.
はい、というわけでゲストパートとソロパートでしたー。
Right, so that was the guest part and solo part.
どうでしたか？
How was it?
ゲストパートはね、メルを、おかゆところねと歌いましたね。
For the guest part, we sang with Meraru, Okayu, and Korone.
まず一曲目から始まって、正座慣れたら白上フブキ、フブキちゃんとすいちゃんが来てくれました。
First song started, and when I sat in seiza, Fubuki-chan and Suichan came.
天使に触れたので、先長と歌ってから、ふぶちゃんと歌いました。
Since I touched on angels, I sang with Suichan first, and then Korone and Fubuchan.
いや、しょんね、ぺこちゃん、とMCをやったんだけど、まさか手紙を読んでくれると思わなくて。
Shion's Peko-chan... and did MC, but I never thought they'd read me a letter!
なんか正直本当にあのピコニーが勝っちゃって、あの「えっ？手紙書いてきてくれたの？」ってなって
Seriously, Peko-ni really won, and I was like, "Eh? You wrote a letter?"
「えっ、えっ、本当にえっ？」みたいな感じのまま、感情のままだったから
and I was like, "Eh? Really? Eh?" and just stayed like that.
ちょっと驚きを隠せなかったんだけど、いや本当に嬉しい、今ちょっとウルッとね、聞いてて思いました。
I couldn't really show my surprise, but I was so happy listening to it, you know?
そうぺこちゃんと、からふると歌って、MCにも出てもらいました。
So Peko-chan and Korone sang, and MC joined in too.
で、明日の夜空、紹介ハーモニ期生で歌いました。
Then, "Asunoyo Sora", we sang in Harmonic Class.
集まってくれてありがとな。
Thanks for coming, Sakamita!
え、で、スパークルを、逆真黒え、逆真と一緒にね、スパークル歌いました。
And then, Sparkle, we sang with Sakamata Kuroe, together with Sakamata.
いや、成功するかちょっとわからなかったんですけど、魔法が成功したみたいで、召喚されてきてくれました歯ブラシで。
I wasn't sure if magic would work, but magic seemed to work, and she was summoned with a toothbrush.
「また、またいつでも読んでくださいね」とか言ってたけど、卒業ライブなんだこっちは。
She was like, "Read it again anytime," but this is my graduation live!
五月卒業するんだわ。
You're the one graduating!
はい、さかまたありがとね、来てくれて。
Yeah, Sakamata, thanks for coming!
で、ソロ曲の、ときのめ最終戦争とただ声一つ、2連続で歌わさせていただきました。
And for the second song, we sang "Tokiname Final War" and "Tada Koe Hitotsu" back-to-back.
どうだったでしょうか？
How was it?
手紙ね、手紙本当にびっくりしたね。
The letter, the letter really surprised me!
そのさかまたもね、本当に海のびっくりしてたわ、びっくりした？
And Sakamata also, I was really surprised by Umi, were you surprised?
びっくりしてそうだわ。
I'd be surprised, right?
「ありがとね」とか、コメント早すぎてさ、見れでよ。
"Thank you," and all that—I read the comments too fast.
早すぎるよコメント、いかないで、卒業します。
Comments are too fast, I can't read them.
というわけでね、あと2曲となりました。次に歌う曲なんですが
So, we have two more songs left. The next song we're singing...
実は、この配信をするにあたり、何を最後にみんなにね、伝わったらいいかなっていうのを考えてたんですよ。
Actually, before doing this stream, I was thinking about what I wanted to convey to everyone at the end.
その中で、実はホロライブの公式ページにあるシオンのプロフィール
Among that, actually, on the Hololife official page, Shion's profile...
公式ページのプロフィールって何なんだよって人がいっぱいそうだけど
There are so many people asking what the official page profile is,
実はあのプロフィール書いてある人結構書いてあるから、
but actually, quite a few people write their profiles,
なんか好きな食べものとか、誕生日、身長とかの下に
so below things like favorite food, birthday, height,
ま、夢って言う欄が、実はあるんですよ。
there is actually a section called "Dream."
ある人とない人がいるかもしれないんだけど。
Some people might have it, and some might not.
実は、その夢のところに、シオンが書いた言葉があるんだけど、「世界のみんなを笑顔にする」なんですよね。
Actually, in that dream section, there's something Shion wrote: "To make everyone in the world smile."
まあ、でも世界のみんなとまではちょっと難しいかもしれないけど、せめてシオンのことを好きでいてくれる人には絶対笑顔でいてほしいと思ったから、
Well, making everyone in the world smile might be a bit difficult, but I really want the people who like Shion to always be smiling,
そんな気持ちで次の歌を歌いたいと思ってます。
so with that feeling, I want to sing my next song.
それでは聴いてください。「メイジ・オブ・ヴァイオレット」
So please listen to... "Mage of Violet."
未来方ばっか見てないで
Don't just look at future ideals,
嘘パパパパラリラ踊れよ
Sing lies, pa-pa-pa-paralira, and dance!
長い学問言う通りせ
Follow long-standing academics,
鮮やかなわがまま称えよ
Praise vibrant selfishness!
いないいないばあでこっち向いて
Turn here with peek-a-boo,
知らんぷりの未来を逆かせよ
and turn the feigned future upside down!
知らん間待って固まって
Waiting cluelessly, freezing up,
だまだま魔法はめて黒魔術
trapping magic step by step, dark arts!
晴れの呼吸に声揃えよ
Align your voices in clear skies,
闇に震え吠えるバロス
Barlos, howling and trembling in the dark.
切実に響く言葉は ぶち切れハードきょうパラダイス
Words echoing earnestly, snapping hard in today's paradise!
きらり心奥底まで届け
Sparkling, reaching deep into the heart,
これからも私の下で
from now on, under my wing,
不思議な力打ち放って
unleash mysterious powers,
世界も笑顔になっちゃって
making the whole world smile too!
パパパパラリラ歌えば
If you sing pa-pa-pa-paralira,
一生一緒だよね
we'll be together forever, right?
暗い文句も忘れないで
Don't forget the gloomy complaints,
黙った体さらば踊れよ
bid farewell to your silent body and dance!
視界がね空かないで
Don't let your vision clear up,
今はただ離れてかないで
for now, just don't drift away.
睨み合ってこっち向いて
Glaring at each other, turn this way,
今はまだ心の順序を
for now, keep the order of your heart
期待最小限に固まって
solidified with minimal expectations,
裏パパパパラリラ動け黒魔術
ura-pa-pa-paralira, move, dark arts!
我にい続け今宵よ
Stay with me tonight,
闇を破れネシアーよ
shatter the darkness, Neschia.
靴底金棒その名は
An iron club on the soles, its name is
眠りの発祥パラダイス
the paradise of slumber's origin.
きらり心奥底まで届け
Sparkling, reaching deep into the heart,
白黒つけてあげるから
because I'll settle things for you,
不思議な力振りかざして
brandishing mysterious powers,
みんなで笑顔になっちゃって
making everyone smile together!
パパパパラリラ歌えば
If you sing pa-pa-pa-paralira,
一生一緒かもね
we might be together forever.
きらり左と紫色に染まって
Sparkling, dyed in left and purple,
これからもあなたのもとで
from now on, right by your side,
奇跡の呪文解き放って
unleashing miraculous spells,
咲かせる笑顔の花を
making the flowers of smiles bloom!
きらり左と紫色に染まって
Sparkling, dyed in left and purple,
これからもあなたのもとで
from now on, right by your side,
奇跡の呪文解き放って
unleashing miraculous spells,
咲かせる笑顔の花を
making the flowers of smiles bloom!
きらり心奥底まで届け
Sparkling, reaching deep into the heart,
これからも変わらないままで
staying unchanged from now on,
不思議な力ほら宿して
behold, harboring mysterious powers,
世界も笑顔になっちゃって
making the whole world smile too!
パパパパラリラ歌えば
If you sing pa-pa-pa-paralira,
一生一緒だよね
we'll be together forever, right?
絶対一緒だよね
Absolutely together forever, right?
はい、というわけで、「メイジ・オブ・ヴァイオレット」でしたー！
Yes, and that was "Mage of Violet"!
歌う前にもね話したんだけど、世界のみんなを笑顔にするということで、特大魔法を使っちゃいました！見てましたかー？
As I talked about before singing, with the goal of making everyone in the world smile, I used an extra-large magic! Were you watching?
虹がかかって、晴天です！
A rainbow appeared, and it's clear skies!
みんなが笑顔になってると嬉しいなと思います。
I hope it makes you happy to see everyone smiling.
というわけで、次が最後の曲になるんだけど、その前にこうやってみんなの前で話すのも…
So, the next song will be the last one, but before that, talking to everyone like this...
今日が最後になると思うから
Since I think today will be my last,
お手紙を書いてきました。
I've written a letter.
では、読みます。
Now, I'll read it.
塩っ子のみんなへ。
To all my Shiokko,
いよいよ今日は卒業ライブ当日だね。
finally today is the day of my graduation live.
ギリギリの新曲聴かせたくて、伝えたくて、
I wanted to let you hear my brand new song and convey it,
今日で言うきのう、卒業ライブ前日に書いて。
I wrote it yesterday, the day before the graduation live.
やば、もう泣きちゃったじゃん、
Oh man, I'm already crying,
まだ全然話してないのに。
and I haven't even really started talking yet.
正直まだちょっとふわふわした不思議な気持ちです。
Honestly, I still have this sort of dreamy, strange feeling.
今日卒業ライブを終えてスタジオを出たら、実感するのかな。
Once the graduation live is over today and I leave the studio, will it sink in?
家に帰ったら実感するのかな。
When I go home, will it sink in?
卒業したんだって思うのかな。
Will I feel like I've graduated?
今は悔いのないようにやり切りたいという気持ちでいっぱいです。
Right now, I'm just full of the desire to give it my all with no regrets.
7年目。
Year 7.
活動期間は6年半。
My activity period was 6 and a half years.
こんなにも長い期間をずっと一緒に歩んでくれたこと、本当にありがとう。
Thank you so much for walking alongside me for such a long time.
休止をしたりしてたくさん待たせてしまったりして、本当にごめんね。
I'm truly sorry for taking breaks and making you wait so much.
辛い思いをさせてしまったなってちょっと心残りです。
I have a lingering regret that I put you through difficult times.
塩っ子のみんなに見てもらいからいろんなこと頑張りたいなって思う中で、
Wanting you all in Shiokko to see me, as I tried my best at various things,
体調を崩してしまったり、不調はどんどん大きくなって、それに対応していくのもなかなか難しくて、
my health broke down, my physical troubles kept growing, and coping with them was quite difficult.
精神面や体調は悪くなる一方で悔しかったです。
My mental and physical condition only worsened, which was so frustrating.
自分のことなんてどうでもいいし、壊れたらそれでもいいと思ってた私ですが、
I used to think my own well-being didn't matter, that if I broke down, that was fine.
長い期間を経てみんなのおかげで少しでも自分を大切にしてあげたいと思うことができるようになりました。
But after a long time, thanks to everyone, I've come to be able to cherish myself just a little bit.
これは普通の人にとっては当たり前のことかもしれないけど、私にとって本当にすごいことなんだよ。
This might be something natural for ordinary people, but for me, it's truly an amazing thing.
みんなのおかげです。いつもたくさん愛を伝えてくれてありがとう。
It's all thanks to everyone. Thank you always for showering me with so much love.
形として届けてくれてありがとう。
Thank you for delivering it in tangible forms.
出会ってくれてありがとう。
Thank you for meeting me.
見つけてくれてありがとう。
Thank you for finding me.
心から感謝でいっぱいです。
My heart is filled with gratitude.
ソロライブで過ごした思い出はずっと忘れません。
I will never forget the memories spent during my solo lives.
この私を支えてくれる運営さん、そして塩っ子のみんなと出会えて本当に幸せでした。ずっと大好きです。
I am truly blessed to have met the management who supported me, and everyone in Shiokko. I love you all forever.
紫咲シオンは死ぬわけではありません。
Murasaki Shion is not dying.
私という存在がいたこと、覚えてくれたら嬉しいなって思います。
I'd be happy if you could remember that someone like me existed.
私もみんなのことを絶対には忘れないからね。
I will definitely never forget you all either.
6年半、本当にありがとうございました。
Thank you truly for the past six and a half years.
最強の魔法使い、紫咲シオンより！
From the strongest spellcaster, Murasaki Shion!
というわけで、昨日、昨日お手紙を書きました。もっと早く書こうかなって思ったんだけど、
And so, yesterday, I wrote the letter. I thought about writing it sooner,
どんな気持ちになってるかなと思って、ギリギリで書いた方がみんなに伝わるのかなって思ってギリギリに書きました。
but wondering what kind of feeling I'd be in, I thought writing it at the very last minute would convey it best, so I wrote it right at the wire.
いや、ちゃんと伝わってると嬉しいです。
Well, I'd be happy if it got across properly.
みんなが幸せになってくれることを願ってます。
I hope everyone becomes happy.
泣いちゃったよ、くそー！
I went and cried, dammit!
それでは次が最後の曲になりますが、ちょっとその前にお水飲んできまーす。
Well then, the next song will be the last one, but before that, I'm going to go drink some water.
いや、ちょっと思った通りにいかないな。
Man, things aren't going quite the way I thought.
はい！というわけで聞いてください、シオン。
Yes! With that said, please listen, Shion.
真っ赤な夕空、青くなる星、
A crimson evening sky, stars turning blue,
心臓を焦がして冷めない温度。
scorching my heart, a warmth that won't cool down.
半端に混ざった声の残響と、
The lingering echo of a half-mixed voice,
半端に混ざった花の色。
and the half-mixed color of flowers.
きっと立ち止まって芽を伸ばしたって、
Surely, even if I stopped and grew sprouts,
咲いた瞬間散ってしまうのでしょう。
they would scatter the moment they bloom.
いっそそれも素敵な景色なんだって、
If only I could have thought, "Even that is a wonderful scenery,"
きっとそんな風に思えたらよかったって。
and felt that way.
言えない、
I can't say it,
I can't say it—
「さよなら」なんてまだ言えないまま魔法が解けていく。
still unable to say "goodbye" as the magic fades away.
バラバラになって花になって風に溶けていく。
Falling apart, becoming flowers, dissolving into the wind.
手を振れないまま黙って立っている。
Standing in silence without being able to wave my hand.
忘れて すぐに
Forget it right away
うーん 全然 歌になってるのかな
Hmm, I wonder if this is even a song...
伝えたい想いを声に出したって
Even when I voiced the feelings I wanted to convey,
こんな言葉なんて言えないんだろう
I suppose I can't say words like these.
大事に思ってしまうからずっと
Because I've always held them so dear,
大事なことが伝わらないんじゃないかって
I worry that what's important won't get across.
知らない
I don't know,
I don't know.
知りたくもないことばっかで
With nothing but things I didn't even want to know,
胸が裂けていく
my heart is tearing apart,
ズタズタになって怖いぐらいに愛しくなっていく
shattered to pieces, becoming frighteningly dear to me.
でも触れないまま 不確かにしてしまう
Yet without even touching you, I leave it uncertain.
ごめんね ごめんね
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
いつか時間が経ってみたら なんでもないって顔をして
If time passes, with a nonchalant face,
寂しさも痛みすらも 抜け落ちて過去になる
even loneliness and pain will slip away into the past.
いつしかそんな日が来たら
If a day like that ever comes,
だったら今は
then right now...
どうしようもないくらい 君を想っている
I'm thinking of you more than I can help.
思い出になんてなんないくらい 君でできている
Made of you so much that it'll never just be a memory.
ずっと気づいてた 気づいてしまったんだ
I'd noticed it all along, I've realized it now.
「忘れて」なんてね 嘘だ
"Forget me," or so I said... Just kidding.
愛しさが 胸を焦がしていく
My love is scorching my heart.
傷になったって憶えていて 忘れないでいて
Remember it even if it becomes a scar, don't ever forget.
もう言えないから
Because I can't say it anymore,
今の言葉を伝う
I'll convey these words now.
笑って また会おう
Smile, let's meet again.
さようなら さようなら
Goodbye, goodbye.
みんな本当に ほんとに ちょっと泣いちゃった
Thank you everyone, truly... I cried a little bit.
最後まで見てくれて 本当にありがとうございました
Thank you so much for watching until the very end.
この6年半 良く7年応援してくれてありがとう
Thank you for supporting me for these 6 and a half, nearly 7 years.
ずっと見てくれてありがとう ずっと愛してくれてありがとう
Thank you for watching over me, thank you for loving me all this time.
バイバイ またね
Bye-bye, see you later!